<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Arbor</title>
    <description>Arbor workflows</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Using PhyloPen</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;evaluating-phylopen&quot;&gt;Evaluating PhyloPen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please try the following exercise to evaluate the current version of our new application PhyloPen. PhyloPen is an interface that lets you interact with a phylogenetic tree and a matching trait matrix to explore features about organisms and their relationships to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any difficulties during the exercises, please feel free to ask for assistance. Also, remember
to consult the tables that show what gestures can be performed in PhyloPen (i.e., pen and multitouch gestures.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before starting, please complete this pre-activity &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1sKxdYsaRTeQTpsUTFE3H77uYpZe08xOjyj_n_YEAOhc/edit?ts=5ba2af03&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The instructions for PhyloPen are &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/PhyloPen/exercise.instructions.phylopen.Sept2018.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Download and save this file somewhere to your computer. Follow these instructions to test the various capabilities of PhyloPen using the supplied tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, attempt to complete the same tasks in Mesquite using these &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/PhyloPen/exercise.instructions.mesquite.Sept.2018.pdf&quot;&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have completed the exercises, please provide feedback using this post-activity &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Xe3d0uOOalzmPhpkF-BRYR5YOTCkqQ0L9_Co-bjDGLY/edit?ts=5ba30ebb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/tutorials/Using-PhyloPen/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/tutorials/Using-PhyloPen/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Obtain a Tree from Open Tree of Life</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-web-services-to-obtain-a-tree-from-opentree&quot;&gt;Use Web Services to Obtain a Tree from OpenTree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web services are protocols for computers to exchange information over the web (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_service&quot;&gt;wikipedia: web service&lt;/a&gt;), typically via an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_programming_interface&quot;&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;. In biology, web services are becoming more and more common. You can obtain, for example, phylogenetic trees from &lt;a href=&quot;http://opentreeoflife.org/&quot;&gt;Open Tree of Life&lt;/a&gt;, geographic occurrences from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gbif.org/&quot;&gt;GBIF&lt;/a&gt;, and trait data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://eol.org/&quot;&gt;Encyclopedia of Life&lt;/a&gt;, all using web services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a number of pre-made functions in Arbor that can obtain data through web services. These functions can be included in workflows that make it easy to combine your data with data obtained over the web and carry out analyses. In this tutorial we will illustrate one of these applications, starting with a list of species and obtaining a phylogenetic tree from Open Tree of Life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-from-a-list-of-species-to-a-phylogenetic-tree&quot;&gt;Example: from a list of species to a phylogenetic tree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to start with a list of species. You can obtain this list as a csv file &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/mammal_species_list.csv&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; download and save this file somewhere to your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, open an Arbor instance (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://arbor.arborworkflows.com&quot;&gt;Arbor web app&lt;/a&gt;). You will now need to load in your species list. You can do this by dragging the file that you just downloaded onto the “Browse or drop files” box:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen1.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(you can also see our tutorial on &lt;a href=&quot;/tutorials/using-the-arbor-webapp/&quot;&gt;using the Arbor webapp&lt;/a&gt;) for more information on loading data into Arbor)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be building a workflow to do this analysis. Note that you need to be logged in and have write access to a collection to make the next parts work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click over to the “Analysis” tab, and create a new workflow. To do that, type the name of the new workflow it the box under “Create new analysis.” Let’s call our workflow “getOTLTreeAndPlot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen2.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have created the workflow, you should be able to view and edit (but right now it is just a blank white space!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen3.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in this workflow is to match the species names with the names in the Open Tree of Life Taxonomy (OTT). To do this, we will use a function in the “fxOpenTree” collection called “Lookup Names Using OpenTree Taxonomy.” Add this function to your workflow using the “+ add to workflow” button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen4.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can click the tab on the left side of that new workflow step to indicate that the user will send a data table directly to this function. So our workflow is now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen5.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to pull out an “induced subtree” from open tree of life using the OTT ids that we obtained in the previous step. To do that, add a new function to your workflow, again from the “fxOpenTree” collection: “Return the OpenTree subtree from a table of OTL node IDs.” Add and connect that next step to your workflow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen6.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add a step to standardize the branch lengths of your tree using the module called “Make Fake Branch Lengths,” also in the “fxOpenTree” collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we just need to plot our resulting tree. You can use a function from the “fxPhylogenyTools” collection called “PlotTreeWithApe.” Add that function, connect it to your workflow, and specify that the last output be sent to the user:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/ott.completed.wf.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen7&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now just click “Setup and run.” In the box that appears, choose your input file with the list of mammal species names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen8.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workflow will run for a while:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen9.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen9&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then finish:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen10.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen10&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can then change to the “visualization” tab, and select the output from your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen11.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen11&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then see the final result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/webServices/webserv-screen12.png&quot; alt=&quot;screen12&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a phylogenetic tree pulled from the Open Tree of Life synthesis that includes all of the species in the table that you supplied.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/tutorials/Use_Open_Tree/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/tutorials/Use_Open_Tree/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to a New Arbor Interface</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-a-new-interface-to-work-with-arbor-apps&quot;&gt;Use a new interface to work with Arbor apps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial will help you use a new Arbor interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First go here and create a user account: (see register in the top right corner)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://54.82.147.249:8080&quot;&gt;http://54.82.147.249:8080&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email Curt (curtislisle@gmail.com) that you have a login, so that he can add you to a user group that can run tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3&quot;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigate to this address (same root with /arbor_apps at the end).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://54.82.147.249:8080/arbor_apps/&quot;&gt;http://54.82.147.249:8080/arbor_apps/]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-4&quot;&gt;Step 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way to try the interface is to load a tree &amp;amp; matrix, then pick a function to run.   To load the tree and matrix, click the tabs at the bottom of the blue bar (e.g. PHYLOGENETIC TREE).  This moves to the “current tree” panel, which will initially be empty.  Next, click on the title “Phylogenetic ‘Tree (.phy)” below (with the white background).  This should open a dialog that lets you browse any collections on this instance for data.  There is an “example data” collection with trees and matrices in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-5&quot;&gt;Step 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeat this process to load a character matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-6&quot;&gt;Step 6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other tabs should appear on the blue bar for each easy-mode function loaded.  Select one of these and click the column from the matrix you want to use to perform the operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-7&quot;&gt;Step 7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see a green “progress circle” with status next to it, like Queued, Running, Pushing Output, and then the output of the method should display.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/tutorials/New-Interface-Tutorial/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/tutorials/New-Interface-Tutorial/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kembel Biodiversity Workflow</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-r-package-picante-to-explore-and-analyze-community-data&quot;&gt;Use R package ‘picante’ to explore and analyze community data.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial will guide the user through Steven Kembel’s biodiversity workflow developed for the R package ‘picante’.  Picante allows users to analyze community ecology data sets in a multivariate and phylogenetic context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documentation for picante can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/picante/index.html&quot;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/picante/index.html&lt;/a&gt;, and the original workflow can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://kembellab.ca/r-workshop/biodivR/SK_Biodiversity_R.html&quot;&gt;http://kembellab.ca/r-workshop/biodivR/SK_Biodiversity_R.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arbor instance we will be using for this tutorial can be located at &lt;a href=&quot;http://52.204.9.236/#&quot;&gt;http://52.204.9.236/&lt;/a&gt;.  To prepare for the tutorial, sign in using your username and password and highlight the eyeball icon next to the KembelBiodiversityWorkshop directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot1b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;loading-example-data&quot;&gt;Loading example data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial will use files containing species traits, species abundances, a species phylogeny, and community metadata. These files are saved in the Arbor instance, and are called:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;species.traits.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;grassland.community.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plot.metadata.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;grassland.phylogeny.newick (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wish to download and view a file, select it from the dropdown list at the bottom of the Arbor homepage and click the download button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-the-data-visualization-and-transformation-workflow&quot;&gt;Run the data visualization and transformation workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we run any analysis on the data, we are first going to transform and standardize it.  To accomplish this, we will use the ‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ workflow.  Begin by clicking on the ‘Analysis’ tab, then select ‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ from the dropdown menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, click on the blue ‘Set up and run’ button.  You will see a popup box listing the outputs of the modules in your workflow.  Note the gray text next to the output; it denotes the format of the output.  For example, &lt;strong&gt;treePlot&lt;/strong&gt;’s output will be formatted as an image.  At the bottom of the box, select the input files&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘species.traits.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ for &lt;strong&gt;traits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘grassland.phylogeny.newick (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ for &lt;strong&gt;phylogeny&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘grassland.community.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ for &lt;strong&gt;comm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘plot.metadata.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’  for &lt;strong&gt;metadata&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start the analysis, click the blue ‘Run’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s have a look at the outputs of our analysis.  Outputs can be viewed under the ‘Visualization’ tab.  To access a given output, select the class of output from the dropdown menu under &lt;strong&gt;select visualization&lt;/strong&gt;.  Next, pull up the output you wish to view from the dropdown menu under &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;.  Finally, click on the blue ‘Update’ button.  You can click the downward pointing chevron to the right of your login information to collapse the interface to get an unobstructed view of your output.  Clicking on this arrow a second time returns the interface to the screen.  Let’s have a look at the transformed data produced by the workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download the output, return to the ‘Data Management’ tab and scroll to the bottom of the screen.  Under &lt;strong&gt;Save or download data&lt;/strong&gt; you are able to select your output from the drop down menu.  Next, select the desired file format (.png or .jpeg for images such as our plots), and click the blue ‘Download’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to save intermediate data files to your Arbor directory to continue using them. For this tutorial, be sure to save these files into the directory called ‘KembelBiodiversityWorkshop’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow metadata 3.csv’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow comm.after.decostand.no.rownames.csv’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow comm.after.decostand.with.rownames.csv’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-the-visualizing-and-summarizing-biodiversity-data-workflow&quot;&gt;Run the visualizing and summarizing biodiversity data workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This workflow allows the user to run preliminary analyses to describe differences in biodiversity between habitats.  The workflow is accessed and initiated in the same manner as before.  Start by clicking the ‘Analysis’ tab, then select ‘KBW.1.enter.visualizing.and.summarizing.biodiversity.data.workflow (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ from the dropdown menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proceed by clicking on the blue ‘Set up and run’ button and selecting the input files.  For this analysis, we will be using files produced by the data visualization and transformation workflow.  These files contain data that have been normalized and reformatted to fit the functions contained in Arbor.  Select ‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow metadata 3.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ for &lt;strong&gt;metadata&lt;/strong&gt; and ‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow comm.after.decostand.no.rownames.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ for &lt;strong&gt;comm.total&lt;/strong&gt;.  The input &lt;strong&gt;column_to_aggregate&lt;/strong&gt;  draws its selection from the metadata file and contains several choices.  For this tutorial, select ‘habitat’.  Finally, click the blue ‘Run’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis has performed a t-test on the number of species between habitats and plotted the inverse Simpson’s index by habitat.  The outputs of this analysis can be visualized in the same fashion as above.  Under the ‘Visualization’ tab select a class of output from the dropdown menu under &lt;strong&gt;select visualization&lt;/strong&gt;, then select the desired output under &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;.  Finally, click on the blue ‘Update’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-the-multivariate-community-analysis-workflow&quot;&gt;Run the multivariate community analysis workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may also be interested in performing multivariate analyses on our data.  To begin, access the multivariate community analysis workflow by clicking the ‘Analysis’ tab and selecting ‘KBW.1.multivariate.community.analysis.workflow (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ from the dropdown menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, click the blue ‘Set up and run’ button and select the input files. As before, this analysis is formatted to accept the files produced by the data visualization and transformation workflow. Select ‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow comm.after.decostand.with.rownames.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ for &lt;strong&gt;comm.total&lt;/strong&gt; and ‘KBW.1.enter.visualize.and.transform.data.workflow metadata 3.csv (KembelBiodiversityWorkshop)’ for &lt;strong&gt;metadata&lt;/strong&gt;. Initiate the analysis by clicking the blue ‘Run’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outputs of this analysis can be visualized as before. Under the ‘Visualization’ tab select a class of output from the dropdown menu under &lt;strong&gt;select visualization&lt;/strong&gt;, then select the desired output under &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;. Finally, click on the blue ‘Update’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examine-the-r-scripts-for-each-module&quot;&gt;Examine the R scripts for each module&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arbor workflows are constructed using modules that can be assembled as needed to fit the specific needs of your analysis.   To view the script for a module, click the ‘Show script’ button under the analysis tab.  You can also choose to download the module as a .json file by clicking on the blue ‘Download’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/KembelBiodiversity/KBWScreenshot11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/tutorials/Kembel-documentation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/tutorials/Kembel-documentation/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spider</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-r-package-spider-to-analyze-species-delimitation-and-test-for-reciprocal-monophyly&quot;&gt;Use R package ‘spider’ to analyze species delimitation and test for reciprocal monophyly.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tutorial will guide the user through the spider workflow.  Spider is an R package that includes several useful tests for DNA barcoding studies that are not contained in other comparative method-focused R packages.  Documentation on Spider can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=spider&quot;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=spider&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Arbor instance we will be using for this tutorial can be reached at &lt;a href=&quot;http://52.204.9.236/#&quot;&gt;http://52.204.9.236/&lt;/a&gt;.  To prepare for the tutorial, sign in using your username and password and highlight the eyeball icon next to the Spider directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spider/ArborScreenshot1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;load-the-example-data&quot;&gt;Load the example data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Species delimitation projects using molecular information require a multiple sequence alignment, with each species represented by many sequences.  This tutorial will use a &lt;em&gt;Spheniscus&lt;/em&gt; alignment that was prepared using publicly available sequences from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/&quot;&gt;GenBank&lt;/a&gt;, and aligned using the program &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geneious.com/download&quot;&gt;Geneious v9.0.5&lt;/a&gt;.  This file is saved in the Arbor program, and is called ‘Spheniscus_seqs_arbor.csv (Spider)’.  If you wish to download and view the file, select ‘Spheniscus_seqs_arbor.csv (Spider)’ from the dropdown list at the bottom of the Arbor homepage and click the download button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spider/ArborScreenshot2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-the-spider-workflow&quot;&gt;Run the Spider workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A preassembled workflow has been constructed in Arbor.  To access it, click on the ‘Analysis’ tab, then select ‘Spider2.0’ from the dropdown menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spider/ArborScreenshot3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, click on the blue ‘Set up and run’ button.  You will see a popup box listing the outputs of the modules in your workflow.  Note the gray text next to the output; it denotes the format of the output.  For example, &lt;strong&gt;Phylogeny&lt;/strong&gt;’s output will be formatted as an image.  In the middle of the box, select the input file ‘Spheniscus_seqs_arbor.csv’ from the dropdown menu.  To start the analysis, click the blue ‘Run’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spider/ArborScreenshot5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s have a look at the outputs of our analysis.  Outputs can be viewed under the ‘Visualization’ tab.  To access a given output, select the class of output from the dropdown menu under &lt;strong&gt;select visualization&lt;/strong&gt;.  Next, pull up the output you wish to view from the dropdown menu under &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;.  Finally, click on the blue ‘Update’ button.  You can click the downward pointing chevron to the right of your login information to collapse the interface to get an unobstructed view of your output.  Clicking on this arrow a second time returns the interface to the screen.  Let’s have a look at the Phylogeny produced by the Spider2.0 workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spider/ArborScreenshot6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download the output, return to the ‘Data Management’ tab and scroll to the bottom of the screen.  Under &lt;strong&gt;Save or download data&lt;/strong&gt; you are able to select your output from the drop down menu.  Next, select the desired file format (.png or .jpeg for images such as our phylogeny), and click the blue ‘Download’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spider/ArborScreenshot7.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examine-the-r-scripts-for-each-module&quot;&gt;Examine the R scripts for each module&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arbor workflows are constructed using modules that can be assembled as needed to fit the specific needs of your analysis.  To view the script, click the ‘Show script button’ under the analysis tab. You can also choose to download the module as a .json file by clicking on the blue ‘Download’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Spider/ArborScreenshot4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/tutorials/Spider-Tutorial/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/tutorials/Spider-Tutorial/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>BiSSE</title>
        <description>&lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;0;url=http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/bisse/&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be automatically forwarded to the Arbor app. If not, click &lt;a href=&quot;http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/bisse/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/arborapps/otsapps/bisse/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/arborapps/otsapps/bisse/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Phylomap</title>
        <description>&lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;0;url=http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/phylomap/&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be automatically forwarded to the Arbor app. If not, click &lt;a href=&quot;http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/phylomap/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/arborapps/otsapps/phylomap/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/arborapps/otsapps/phylomap/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Slowdown test</title>
        <description>&lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;0;url=http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/slowdown/&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be automatically forwarded to the Arbor app. If not, click &lt;a href=&quot;http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/slowdown/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/arborapps/slowdown/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/arborapps/slowdown/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Map occurences</title>
        <description>&lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;0;url=http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/occurrences/&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be automatically forwarded to the Arbor app. If not, click &lt;a href=&quot;http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/occurrences/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/arborapps/occurrences/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/arborapps/occurrences/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Matrix Explorer</title>
        <description>&lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;refresh&quot; content=&quot;0;url=http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/matrixExplorer/&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be automatically forwarded to the Arbor app. If not, click &lt;a href=&quot;http://arbor.arborworkflows.com/matrixExplorer/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/arborapps/matrixExplorer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/arborapps/matrixExplorer/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
